TAPAN PATRA

R&D Test Lead

9703811214 • tapankpatro@gmail.com • https://www.linkedin.com/in/tapan-kumar-patra-4b115824/ • Hyderabad, India

Summary

With 14+ years of professional testing experience, I excel in requirements analysis, test strategy development, comprehensive documentation, API testing, test automation (C#, Python stack), developing test data, write script, test platform configuration, bug reporting, and advocating for testability. My agile ability ensures effective test planning and execution, consistently delivering high-quality software products.

Key Skills

- * Test Automation | Testing | Agile Scrum | C# | Python | Selenium | Azure | Selenium
- * Critical Thinking | Team Leadership
- * AVEVA PDMS | AVEVA System Platform SCADA | AVEVA ERM | Aras PLM |

Experience

AVEVA Hyderabad, India R&D Team Lead 6/2019 – Present

- Leading a team of 4 QA engineers to ensure the delivery of high-quality engineering and industrial automation software in azure cloud.
- · Handle customer communications and understand the business logic and the technical side of the application under test.
- Oversaw the execution of manual and automated test cases, analyzing results and reporting defects to the development team. Collaborate closely with development teams to create effective test strategies and plans. Ensure comprehensive test coverage for all features and functionalities.
- Facilitate team's planning and removing impediments of the team to achieve the sprint goals/deliverables while coaching agile principles.
- Managed and mentored a team of four testers, including resource allocation, task assignments, and performance evaluations, support the onboarding process for new testers at team level.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams, including development, design, and marketing, to align on product vision, goals, and development timelines, fostering a cohesive and efficient work environment.
- Helped Product Owner to manage and refine the product backlog to create clear and detailed user stories, acceptance criteria, and prioritization, enabling the team to work effectively and deliver valuable features.
- Applied agile methodologies Scrum to help iterative development, conducting regular reviews and demos, gathering stakeholder feedback, and making data-driven adjustments to enhance the product.
- Functioned as the primary point of contact for internal and external stakeholders, effectively communicating product updates, status, and roadmaps, fostering strong relationships, and ensuring alignment.

AVEVA Hyderabad, India
Senior Test Engineer 9/2014 - 6/2019

- · Drive the evaluation and adoption of test automation tools and frameworks to increase testing efficiency.
- Working in a DevOps Microservices environment using tools such as Postman, JMeter, Azure DevOps for CI Testing.
- · Developed test scripts using C#, Selenium, Restsharp, specflow, Teststack.white, Appium, Nunit.

Cognizant Hyderabad, India
Test Engineer 4/2010 - 8/2014

- Test case creation, Test execution, defects management and reporting using HP-QC.
- · Design and develop test automation framework using QTP.

Education

Biju Patnaik University of Technology

BTech Electronics and Communication

2005 - 2009

Courses

- AVEVA Leadership Foundation | AVEVA Management Development Program | Cognixia Azure Administrator |
- * STQC Certified Test Manager | Pluralsight Path Using the Scrum Framework